Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Special Events and Activities, War Demonstration Hospital FA012
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Special Events and Activities, War Demonstration Hospital
1916-1920, 1959, undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Stewart, Major George A.
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. War Demonstration Hospital
Rockefeller University
FA012
4.15 Cubic Feet 18 document cases
Arrangement
This collection consists of 9 series: 1. Class records, 2. Correspondence, 3. Hospital records, 4. Instructional Material, 5. Photographs, 6. Printed Materials, 7. Reports, 8. Major George A. Stewart, 9. Superintendents' files.
Biographical / Historical
The War Demonstration Hospital at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research had its beginnings in a hospital that Alexis Carrel set up in Compiegne, France in August, 1914. In a hotel building donated by the French government and with a $20,000 grant from the Rockefeller Foundation, Carrel set up a special hospital to combine research with treatment in order to find better methods of combating severe bacterial infections of lacerated wounds. Henry Drysdale Dakin, an English biochemist who had worked for a time with Christian Herter at the RIMR, joined Carrel. Dakin developed a solution of sodium hypochlorite buffered with sodium bicarbonate that was used in the irrigation of wounds after radical surgery removed the injured tissue.
When the United states entered World War I, the Rockefeller Foundation again gave money to Carrel to set up a hospital where American and French military surgeons could be trained in the Carrel-Dakin treatment. In six weeks, the grounds of the Institute accommodated sixteen portable hospitals. each of the hospitals had two wards of 25 beds each and an operating pavilion. The designs for these temporary hospitals were tested for their applicability to the conditions at the front.
Twice each month, beginning August 2, 1917 and lasting until March 29, 1919, doctors were assigned to the War Demonstration Hospital by the Surgeon General to take a two-week course in the Carrel-Dakin method. Edric Smith, the Assistant Business Manager, ran the War Demonstration Hospital for Henry James, the Business Manager, who had enlisted in the Army. Major George A. Stewart was assigned to the War Demonstration Hospital by the Surgeon General in September 1917. Stewart had received his medical degree from the Johns Hopkins Medical School and Hospital and had worked at the St. Agnes Hospital in Baltimore. At the War Demonstration Hospital, he organized the clinical service and laboratory courses. On February 14, 1918, Stewart was placed in charge in Carrel's absence and named Surgeon-in-Chief.
Mary L. Whitney was appointed Superintendent of the War Demonstration Hospital, with Eleanor G. Evans as Assistant Superintendent. They supervised the daily operation of the hospital and were in charge of the training of the nurses.
In March, 1919, the RIMR began shutting down the War Demonstration Hospital, which formally closed in April. When used, the Carrel-Dakin treatment was effective; however, the procedure was too involved for military surgeons and required too much equipment and training for civilian surgeons. The treatment ended up being used only for trivial wounds until penicillin was discovered, when it was discarded altogether.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes photographs, correspondence, memos, and clippings. Also present in the collection are student evaluations, background notes, and tests, as well as daily reports, statistics, and inventories.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to this collection is restricted pending permission from Rockefeller University.
Related Materials
See Also:
FA137 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Subject Files, Boxes 9, 30 and 73.
FA013 Rockefeller University records, Assistant Business Manager, Subject Files, Boxes 29 and 32.
FA211 Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Treasurer/Assistant Treasurer, Box 1. FA211 Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Secretary, Box 1. FA211 Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Secretary's File, Box 2.
FA214 Rockefeller University records, Director of Administrative Services, Roger C. Elliot, Reports: Bursar's Receipts and Disbursements, Box 13.
FA231 Alexis Carrel papers, Rockefeller University Faculty.
Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Counsel, Box 1.
FA236 Rockefeller University records, Rockefeller University Press, Graphic Services, Photographs, Groups and Special Events.
See Archivist for identification of related materials and further assistance.
Separated Materials
Oversized item: "The War Demonstration Hospital. Its Plan and Construction." New York: The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1917. (duplicates of booklet in hard-back bound volume).
See Rockefeller University records, Miscellaneous, Oversized.
File Plan
Former Classification: I 600.2
Medical care; Radiology; World War I; Radiation; Prevention and health; Medicine, Preventive; Medical education; Hospitals
- Class Records, 1917-1919; 1; 0.6 Cubic Feet
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Includes photographs and evaluations of students; also includes correspondence, students' background notes, and tests.
  - November 5-16, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - November 19-30, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - December 3, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - January 2, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - January 14, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - January 28, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - February 11, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - February 25, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - March 11, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - March 25, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - April 8, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - April 22, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - May 6, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - May 20, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - June 3, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - June 17, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - July 1, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - July 15, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - July 29, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - August 12, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - August 26, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - September 9, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - September 23, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - October 7, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - October 28, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - November 4, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - November 18, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - December 2, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - December 9, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - December 28, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - January 11, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - January 27, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - February 10, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - February 24, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - March 10, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - March 24, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1917-1919, 1959; 2; 2 folders
  Materials in this section include correspondence and memos. Subjects include the construction of the War Demonstration Hospital and the disposition of case histories.
  - 1917-1919 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Hospital Records, 1917-1919, n.d.; 3; 3 Cubic Feet
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Materials in this section include daily reports, index cards, inventories, and statistics. Subjects include names of men assigned to the War Demonstration Hospital for training, with grades, patient and payroll statistics, and supplies.
  - Inventories, 1917-1919 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Laundry Lists, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Laundry Lists, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Laundry Lists, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Files, 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Newman Clock Company Logs, 1918-1919 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Patient Statistics, 1917-1919 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Payroll and Christmas Prayer, 1917-1920 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Supplies - Orders (A-B), 1917-1919 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Supplies - Orders (C-V), 1917-1919 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Supplies - Orders - Reconstruction: Mr. Spies, 1917-1919 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Supplies - Orders (W), 1917-1919 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Supplies - Orders Received, 1917-1919 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Telephone Call Lists, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Telephone Call Lists, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chemistry Class Cards (Box 5)
  - Doctor's Files - Reference for Hospitals (Box 5)
  - Handwritten Cards - Incomplete (Box 5)
  - Daily Reports, 1917-1919 (Box 6)
  - Grades for Trainees (A-G) (Box 7)
  - Grades for Trainees (H-O) (Box 8)
  - Grades for Trainees (P-Z) (Box 9)
  - Names of Men Assigned to Institute for Training, September 2-7, 1918 (Box 10)
  - Names of Men Assigned to Institute for Training, 1918-1919 (Box 10)
  - Names of Men Assigned to Institute for Training (A-E) (Box 11)
  - Names of Men Assigned to Institute for Training (F-L) (Box 12)
  - Names of Men Assigned to Institute for Training (M-R) (Box 13)
  - Names of Men Assigned to Institute for Training (S-Z) (Box 14)
- Instructional Material, 1917-1918, n.d.; 4; 3 folders
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Includes a course list and reports. Subjects include Carrel's method on treatment of infected wounds and Dakin's solution.
  - Carrel Method on Treatment of Infected Wounds, September 1918 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Course List, May 1917 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Dakin's Solution, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
- War Demonstration Hospital Photographs, 1916-1919, n.d.; 5; 6 folders
  Includes photocopies of photographs. Subjects include chemistry class, nurses, a Theodore Roosevelt letter of congratulations to Carrel, and surgical class.
  Photographs
  - Chemistry Class, 1917 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Joseph P. Meehan, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Class, undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Theodore Roosevelt Letter to Carrel, November 29, 1916 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Surgical Class, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Women (Nurses), 1918 (Box 15, Folder 9)
- Printed Materials, 1917, n.d.; 6; 4 folders
  Includes announcements, articles, catalogues, and newspaper clippings.
  - Announcements re: War Demonstration Hospital, undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Humphreys Sectional Building, undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - "The Modern Hospital" Article on War Demonstration Hospital, August 1917 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, July 1917 (Box 15, Folder 13)
- Reports, 1916-1919; 7; 3 folders
  Includes reports by Carrel and Flexner. Subjects include the hospital at Compiegne and the War Demonstration Hospital.
  - Alexis Carrel, 1916-1919 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Simon Flexner, 1918-1919 (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - General, 1919 (Box 15, Folder 16)
- Major George A. Stewart, 1917-1919, n.d.; 8; 0.6 Cubic Feet
  Arranged in 3 subseries:
  A. Correspondence B. Reports C. Subject Files
  - Correspondence, 1917-1919; A; 0.4 Cubic Feet
    Arranged alphabetically and then chronologically within each letter.
    Includes correspondence, memos, and telegrams. Subjects include answers to inquiries about medical cases and the use of the Carrel-Dakin treatment. Correspondents include Simon Flexner, John G. Long, Joseph P. Meehan, and the Navy.
    - A, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - B, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - C, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - D, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - E, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - F, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - G, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - H, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - I, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - J, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - K, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - L, 1917-1919 (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - M, 1917-1919 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - N, 1918-1919 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - O, 1918 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - P, 1917-1919 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Q-R, 1917-1919 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - S, 1917-1919 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - T, 1918-1919 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - U-V, 1918-1919 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - W-Z, 1917-1919 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Reports, 1919, n.d.; B; 2 folders
    Includes reports on hospital and other topics.
    - Hospital, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 1919 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Subject Files, 1917-1919; C; 0.2 Cubic Feet
    Includes correspondence, memos, notes, and reports. Subjects include the Carrel method, the Dakin solution, empyema, radium, students' reports on use of Carrel-Dakin treatment at camps, tethelin, and X-rays.
    - A-C, 1917-1918 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Dakin Solution/Carrel Method, 1917-1919 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - E-G, 1918 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Empyema, 1918-1919 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - H-P, 1917-1918 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Radium, 1917-1918 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Recommendations to Surgeon General, 1918-1919 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - S-T, 1917-1918 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Students' Reports, 1917-1918 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Tethelin, 1918-1919 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - X-Ray, 1918-1919 (Box 17, Folder 4)
- Superintendents' Files, 1917-1919; 9; 0.2 Cubic Feet
  Arranged in 2 subseries:
  A. Correspondence B. Miscellaneous
  - Correspondence, 1917-1919; A; 0.2 Cubic Feet
    Arranged alphabetically, then chronologically within each letter.
    Includes correspondence, memos, and telegrams. Subjects include nursing staff positions, special materials needed for the hospital, and visits to see the War Demonstration Hospital in operation. Correspondents include Eleanor G. Evans (Assistant Superintendent), Henry James, M. Kenzel, and Mary L. Whitney (Superintendent).
    - A, 1917-1919 (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - B, 1917-1919 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - C, 1917-1918 (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - D, 1917-1918 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - E-G, 1917-1918 (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - H, 1917-1919 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - I-J, 1917-1918 (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - K, 1917-1919 (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - L, 1918-1919 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - M, 1917-1918 (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - N-R, 1917-1919 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - S, 1917-1918 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - T-V, 1917-1919 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - W, 1917-1919 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - X-Z, 1917-1918 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1917-1919; B; 1 folder
    Includes correspondence, notes, and telegrams.
    - 1917-1919 (Box 18, Folder 5)